<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook v4.4//EN"
  "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd">

<article>
  <artheader>
    <title>Scanning</title>
    <author>
      <firstname>Adriano</firstname>
      <surname>Marques</surname>
      <copyright>
        <year>2006</year>
	<holder>Adriano Monteiro Marques</holder>
      </copyright>
    </author>
  </artheader>

  <section>
    <title>Warning</title>
    <para>
      This documentation is not finished! Part or all of it's content may be missing 
      or inaccurate. As Umit is under constant development and improvement, expect
      changes in this documentation at upcoming releases.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <para><application>Umit</application> was designed to accomodate and run more than one
    scan at time. Each scan is executed and shown inside a <emphasis>Scan Tab</emphasis>,
    which has a title and organize every information obtained in the scan result.</para>
    <para>The <emphasis>Scan Tab</emphasis> tries to facilitate your life, by making the 
    informations easier to navigate and search for a given information. Usually, if you wanted
    to scan an entire network using <application>Nmap</application>, you would have to open
    up your favorite terminal, type an entire <application>Nmap</application> command, like
    this one: <command>nmap -A -F -n -T4 192.168.1.1-254</command> and when it finally finishes
    you'll end up with a bunch of lines in the terminal that can hardly be searched and 
    read. If your goal was to know which of the 200 hosts found are serving ssh, what were 
    you going to do? Maybe it won't seen impossible for you, (and it's not) but surely it's
    a boring task that gets worst when you have to do that more than once.</para>
    <para>An answer to your problem is <application>Umit</application>, that can handle this
    task easily, with just a couple of clicks.</para>
    <para>So, if you're wondering if you should retire the command line, I would say 
    <emphasis>NO!</emphasis>. The <application>Nmap's</application> command interface
    is very usefull when you want to scan a few hosts, and skim the result quickly to make
    a decision. Every good network administrator know how usefull is it to simply call
    <command>nmap localhost</command> to know which services are up, for example. If you're
    at the command line, you won't want to open a graphical application to do so, if you can
    quickly pull off your doubt about what is up or down from were you stand.</para>
    <para><application>Umit</application> is intended to help you manage your network,
    by giving you a better way to examine carefully your network peers. If your intention
    is to <emphasis>know</emphasis> better your network, then <application>
    Umit</application> is what you need.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Starting a scan</title>
    
    <para>To start a scan, you need an empty <emphasis>Scan Tab</emphasis>. At the time you
    starts <application>Umit</application>, a new <emphasis>Scan Tab</emphasis> is made 
    available, and as soon as the main interface is shown, you can start typing the target
    address. If you already used this <emphasis>Scan Tab</emphasis>, you can create a new
    one, by doing one of the following:</para>

    <procedure>
      <title>Use the key-stroke</title>
      <step>The key-stroke that creates a new Scan Tab is <accel>CTRL + T</accel>.</step>
    </procedure>

    <procedure>
      <title>Single click on the Create new Scan Tab button Icon in the Main Toolbar</title>
      <step>The Create new Scan Tab button is the <guibutton>1st button in the Main Toolbar
      from left to right.</guibutton></step>
    </procedure>

    <procedure>
      <title>Acces from the Main Menu</title>
      <step>Go to the <emphasis>Main Menu</emphasis> (the one on the top of the application),
	<guimenu>File</guimenu>-&gt;<guimenuitem>New Scan</guimenuitem>.</step>
    </procedure>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Setting a Target</title>

    <para>By the moment you start <application>Umit</application> or create a new scan tab,
    you can start typing the address of the target(s) that you want to scan. Every target
    inserted into the Target field is recorded and remembered in case you need it in the 
    future. As this field features an auto-completation, it's going to be easy the reuse of
    targets.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Conducting a scan</title>
    
    <para># Selecting the profile</para>
    <para># Customizing the command that is going to be executed</para>
    <para># Nmap Output refresh</para>
    <section>
      <title>Known issues</title>

      <para># Non-root user</para>
      <para># Overlapping two scans, by clicking twice on the Start Scan button</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Making Umit usefull enough for your every-day scanning</title>

    <para># Quick list of usefull features for network administrators</para>

    <section>
      <title>The Hosts/Services View</title>

      <para># What does it show</para>
      <para># How to put in order?</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>The Ports/Hosts Page</title>

      <para># What does it show</para>
      <para># Sorting</para>
      <para># Grouping</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Nmap Output Page</title>

      <para># The Highlight mode</para>
      <para># How to change colors</para>
      <para># How does it works the automatic refresh</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Scan Details Page</title>

      <para># What informations are expected to be there</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Host Details Page</title>

      <para># How does it works</para>
      <para># Comments</para>
      <para># The Host Status</para>
      <para># The icons (os and vl)</para>
    </section>
  </section>

</article>